A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Audiovisual Materials, Lectures and Assorted Events FA953
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Audiovisual Materials, Lectures and Assorted Events
1962-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University Press
FA953
6 Cubic Feet 5 storage cartons
5 storage cartons. Unless otherwise noted, all tapes are 7 inch reels.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited with the Rockefeller University archives by the Rockefeller University Press, January 1976.
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order A, B, 1-143. They are numbered consecutively, but in some cases, as for example, The Christmas Lectures, they have been removed from this collection and maintained separately. Starting 1975 The Rockefeller University Lectures have also been maintained separately.
Scope and Contents
The consecutive listing which follows covers the 1962-1975 group of taped events. The card catalog has been used to supply author/title or subject approach to the collection.
Consists of a group of tapes which recorded some Rockefeller University events from 1962-1975. They are numbered A, B, 1 — 143 and include addresses at Convocations; Sigma Xi Lectures; Seminars for Science Writing Fellows; Darwin Lectures; The Rockefeller Institute Lectures; Conferences; AAAS Lectures or Discussions; The Forum, etc.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 550
Medicine, Preventive; Medical sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Medical technology; Science -- Study and teaching; Medical research; Medical education; Life sciences; Rockefeller University Press
- Lectures and assorted events, 1962-1975
  - Richard Strauss - Processional for festival occasions (Box 1, Tape A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  - Miscellaneous processionals (Box 1, Tape B)
  - Convocation, 1962 June 5 (Box 1, Tape 1)
  - Convocation, 1963 June 12 (Box 1, Tape 2-3)
  - Leon Brillouin - Sigma Xi lecture. Information theory and the fundamental assumptions of scientific research, 1964 April 9 (Box 1, Tape 4)
  - N.D. Zinder, V.G. Allfrey, E.L. Tatum, I. Tamm, A.G. Bearn - Seminar for Science writing fellows. Biochemical Genetics, 1964 May 14 (Box 1, Tape 5-8)
  - Convocation, 1964 June 12 (Box 1, Tape 9-10)
  - J. Robert Oppenheimer - Rockefeller Institute Lecture. Niels Bohr and the atomic nucleus, 1964 November 18 (Box 1, Tape 11)
  - Ragnar Granit - (2 lectures by Prof, of neurophysiology), ? 19?, 1965 (Box 1, Tape 12)
  - Alfred Mirsky, Sam Granick, Eric Davidson, Igor Tamm - Seminar for science writing fellows Variable gene activity, 1965 March 18 (Box 1, Tape 13)
  - Conference: Law and the social role of science, 1965 April 8-9 (Box 1, Tape 14-15)
  - Peter Brian Medawar - 4 Lectures (Box 1, Tape 16)
    - Do new advances in medicine lead to genetic deterioration, 1965 April 19
    - Hypothesis and Imagination, 1965 April 20
    - Recent Research on Transplantation Immunity, 1965 April 21
    - A Biology Retrospect, 1965 April 22
  - Convocation, 1965 June 9 (Box 1, Tape 17)
  - Avery Gateway - Memorial Dedication, 1965 September 29 (Box 1, Tape 18)
  - Channel 13 American Institute of Physics - Half-hour sound film The Particle Jungle, 1965 November 22 (Box 1, Tape 19)
  - John McGahern (Irish poet) - Forum.: The Image, 1966 February 8 (Box 1, Tape 20)
  - Peter Weiss - Seminar on Marat/Sade: Experience of writing for the theatre, 1966 April 26 (Box 1, Tape 21)
  - Alfred (Author of Hogan's Goat) - Forum, 1966 May 16 (Box 1, Tape 22)
  - Cohen, E.G.D. - Four Collisions Between Three spheres moving without friction in space, 1966 May 18; 1 minute film (Box 1, Tape 23)
  - Convocation, 1966 June 9 (Box 1, Tape 23 (1))
  - Peyton Rous - Nobel News Conference, 1966 October 13 (Box 1, Tape 24)
  - E.W. Leader - Research Colloquium: The Concept of Unity in Mechanisms of Disease, 1967 February 17; 5 inch tape (Box 1, Tape 25)
  - Peter Marler - Research Colloquium: The Role of acoustical experience in song development of birds, 1967 March 3 (Box 1, Tape 26)
  - George Taylor, Frans A Stafleu - Opening exhibition Address: Three centuries of Botany in North America, 1967 March 20 (Box 1, Tape 27)
  - Peter Denetz, John Hirsch, Georgio De Santillana - Galileo and Brecht: Three statements and a discussion, 1967 March 27 (Box 1, Tape 28)
  - Wolf Kahn - Forum: The Uneasy Rapprochement between Art and Technology, 1967 April 12 (Box 1, Tape 29-29A)
  - Russell Sage Foundation - Conference On Biology & Behavior (Box 1, Tape 30)
    - Environmental Influences (Box 1, Tape 31)
    - Early nutritional Deficiencies am, 1967 April 21 (Box 1, Tape 32)
    - Intrahuman studies of social isolation pm, 1967 April 21 (Box 1, Tape 32)
    - Social implications of early environmental influences, 1967 April 21 (Box 1, Tape 32)
    - Reinforcement and interpersonal Relations am, 1967 April 22 (Box 1, Tape 32)
    - The effects of cultural deprivation pm, 1967 April 22 (Box 1, Tape 32)
  - Convocation, 1967 June 7 (Box 1, Tape 33)
  - Maurice Ewig - Governor's Conference on Oceanography, 1967 October 11 (Box 2, Tape 34-37)
    - J. Lamar Worzal - Studies at Lamont Geological Observatory, 1967 October 12
    - Kenneth O. Emery - The Continental Shelf and Its Resources
    - Marik Talevari - Recent geophysical Studies on Mid-ocean Ridges
    - P.R. Burkholder - Research in the Life Sciences at Lamont Geophysical Observatory
    - John H. Ryther - Some views on the Potential Food Resources of the Sea
    - Ross F. Nigrelli - The New York Aquarium and the Osborn Laboratories of Marine Sciences as a Center for Marine Biological Research in NY City
    - John C. Baiardi - A Marine Research Center operated by a Consortium of Universities located "One Hundred Miles at Sea"
    - N.P. Fofonoff - Measurements of Ocean Currents
    - John P. Breslin - The Main Effects of Form on Ship Motions In a Seaway
    - Wm. O. Rainnie, Jr. - The Use of Deep Submersible ALVIN in Oceanography
    - John I. Ewing - History of The Ocean Basins Recorded in the Sediments
    - Noel B. McLean - The Economics of Marine Science
    - W.J. Pierson, Jr. - Phenomena at The Air-sea Interface
    - Gerhard Newman - Physical Oceanographic Studies at New York Universities
    - Robert D. Wildman - The Sea Grant Concept
  - H. Keffer Hartline - Nobel News Conference, 1967 October 13 (Box 2, Tape 38)
  - D. Bronk; Ld. Adrian G.H. Bishop; Ali Monnier; H.C. Kinsey; David Lloyd; Francis Schmitt; Lorente de No - Gasser Hall Dedication, 1967 October 18 (Box 2, Tape 39)
  - Archibald Macleish - Ellery Sedgwick. Memorial Lecture: Heaven and Earth and the Cage of Form, 1967 February 11 (Box 2, Tape 40-40A)
  - L. Pearce Williams; Ralph E. Gibson; Richard M. Bozorth Nathaniel Frank Ernst Weber Raymond J. Seeger - AAAS Symposium: Michael Faraday, Natural Philosopher PM, 1967 December 26 (Box 2, Tape 41-45)
  - Roger Revelle Athelstan Spilhaus E.A. Mason; William Paddock; Bans W. Singer - AAAS Frontiers of Science Lecture III: Can the Poor Countries Benefit from the Scientific Revolution? PM, 1967 December 26 (Box 2)
  - Ronald King - AAAS Lecture: Faraday and The Unity of Natural Forces AM, 1967 December 29 (Box 2)
  - B.F. Skinner - AAAS Lecture: Teaching Science in High School What is wrong? PM, 1967 December 29 (Box 2)
  - Gerard Piel, Lester Breslow, Lewis Thomas, Kerr White - AAAS Panel Discussion: Public Authority and Public Initiative in the Delivery of Personal Health Services AM, 1967 December 30 (Box 2)
  - Gerard Holton, Michael Polanyi, John R. Platt, Ernest Nagel, Barry Commoner - AAAS Informal Discussion: Do Life Processes Transcend Physics and Chemistry PM, 1967 December 30 (Box 2)
  - Alan Hodgkin - Dame Hester Adrian Memorial Lecture: The Relation between Electrical and Mechanical Events in Muscle, 1968 January 17 (Box 2, Tape 46)
  - Alistair Taylor - American Teilhard de Chardin Association: Man The Model-Maker: The Relationship of Conceptual and Spatial Boundaries, 1968 March 5 (Box 2, Tape 47)
  - David Rockefeller - Committee for a Democratic Society/Forum. What Private Enterprise means for Latin America, 1968 April 1; 48A is a duplicate (Box 2, Tape 48-48A)
  - Science Writers' Seminar, 1968 April 12; 2 copies (Box 2, Tape 49)
  - Aaron Copland - Forum. The Composer's Experience, 1968 May 16 (Box 2, Tape 50)
  - Aaron Copland - Forum. The New York Theatre, 1968 May 21 (Box 2, Tape 51)
  - René J. Dubos - The Human Environment in Technological Societies, 1968 June 3 (Box 2, Tape 52)
  - René J. Dubos - Convocation, 1968 June 11 (Box 2, Tape 53)
  - René J. Dubos - Harvey Lecture, 1968 September 19 (Box 2, Tape 54)
  - René J. Dubos - Installation of Dr. Seitz as President of RU, 1968 October 8 (Box 2, Tape 55)
  - J.L. Gowans - Harvey Lecture: Lymphocytes, 1968 November 14 (Box 2, Tape 56)
  - Ada Louise Huxtable - Forum: Architecture in Hew York, 1968 December 16 (Box 2, Tape 57)
  - Choppin, Tamm - Christmas Lecture, 1968 December 28-29 (Box 2, Tape 58)
  - Pfaffmann, Carl - Symposium on Olfaction and Taste, 1968 August 19-21 (Box 2, Tape 59-61)
    This item is unavailable.
  - Bruce Merrifield - Press Conference: "Synthesizing Enzymes", 1969 January 16 (Box 2, Tape 62)
  - Curtis Williams - Separate Roles for Membrane-Bound and Free Ribosomes in Protein Biosynthesis, 1969 January 16 (Box 2, Tape 63)
  - Curtis Williams - Science Writer's Seminar, 1968 November 26 (Box 2, Tape 64)
  - A. Turkevitch - Chemical Analysis of the Moon Surface RU Lecture, 1969 January 21 (Box 2, Tape 65)
  - F. Seitz - Meeting with Junior Faculty (98), 1969 January 23 (Box 2, Tape 66)
  - Jacques Monod - On the Mechanisms and Significance of Allosteric Interactions, 1969 January 22 (Box 2, Tape 67)
  - Lee Ehrman - RU Research Colloquium. Sexual Behavior and Frequency Dependent Natural Selection, 1969 January 24 (Box 2, Tape 68)
  - Ronald Dworkin - Philosophy Colloquium. The Concept of Obligation and Judicial Review, 1969 January 31 (Box 2, Tape 69)
  - Thos. M. Folds - Lectures in Art: Idea into Image, from sketch to completed work, 1969 February 13 (Box 3, Tape 70)
  - Ruth Bennett - Scientists Committee for Public Information, 1969 March 4 (Box 3, Tape 71)
  - Evelyn Mauss - Facts about Race (Box 3)
  - René Dubos - Responsibility in Science: The Future and the University, 1969 March 4 (Box 3, Tape 72)
  - Paul Goodman - Responsibility in Science: Function of the University (Box 3)
  - James Henderson - RU Research Colloquium. Evidence that Endotoxin aids tiny cancer grafts and nascent chemically-induced tumors, 1969 March 1 (Box 3, Tape 73)
  - John Cooney - Ancient Egyptian Hieroglyphics: Minor Arts of Ancient Egypt, 1969 April 10 (Box 3, Tape 74)
  - Sam Goudsmit - Ancient Egyptian Hieroglyphics, 1969 April 7-8 (Box 3, Tape 75-76)
  - Jekabs Zvilna - Synthesis of Knowledge and Feeling (Illustrated), 1969 April 21 (Box 3, Tape 77)
  - Jekabs Zvilna - Convocation, 1969 June 13 (Box 3, Tape 78)
  - Mc Carty, Pfaffnann Brink, Penndorf, Seitz - Introduction to The Rockefeller University, 1969 October 22 (Box 3, Tape 79)
  - Sheldon Segal, leader of discussion - AAAS Symposium telecast from Boston "Is there an Optimum Level of Population?", 1969 December 30 (Box 3, Tape 80)
  - Sheldon Segal, leader of discussion - Memorial to Dr. Peyton Rous, 1970 May 19 (Box 3, Tape 81)
  - C.H.G. Oldham - Science and Society in China Since the Cultural Revolution RU Lecture, 1970 May 5 (Box 3, Tape 82)
  - Israel Abramov - Lecture #13 for Dr. Pfaffmann's group, 1969 April 23 (Box 3, Tape 83)
  - Israel Abramov - Junior Faculty Meeting, 1969 March 24 (Box 3, Tape 84)
  - Theodosius Dobzhansky - Man in the Light of Evolutionary Biology I, 1970 October 6 (Box 3, Tape 85)
  - Theodosius Dobzhansky - Man in the Light of Evolutionary Biology II, III, IV, V, 1970 October 13 1970 October 20 1970 October 27 1970 November 3 (Box 3, Tape 86-89)
  - James Hirsch - Christmas Lecture White Cells, 1970 December 28 (Box 3, Tape 90)
  - Zanvil Cohn - Christmas Lecture White Cells, 1970 December 29 (Box 3, Tape 91)
  - Gordon MacDonald - Environmental Quality, II (I not recorded), 1971 January 25 (Box 3, Tape 92)
  - Gordon MacDonald - Fairfield-Osborn Memorial Lecture, 1971 March 23 (Box 3, Tape 93)
  - Peter Marler - Vervet Monkey, 1971 April 12 (Box 3, Tape 94)
  - Peter Marler - Vocalizations of Wild Chimpanzees, 1971 April 13 (Box 3, Tape 95)
  - Caryl Haskins - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: Science and Social Purpose, 1971 October 18 (Box 3, Tape 96)
  - William KcElroy - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: The Utility of Science, 1971 October 19 (Box 3, Tape 97)
  - Harold Himsworth - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: Organization and Growth of Scientific Knowledge, 1971 November 3 (Box 3, Tape 98)
  - Robert S. Morison. See book - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: Problems of Science: Goals and Priorities James A. Shannon "Science and the Evolution RU Press, 1973, 1971 November 10 (Box 3, Tape 99)
  - Walter A. Rosenblith - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: Science, Technology and the University, 1971 December 8 (Box 3, Tape 100)
  - Ivan L. Bennett, Jr. - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy: Support of Research and Graduate Education in The United States, 1971 December 9 (Box 3, Tape 101)
  - Gerald Edelman - Darwin Lectures for Centennial: Molecular Biology of the Immune Response, 1971 November 22
    - I: Antibodies, Immunity and Molecular Recognition (Box 3, Tape 102)
    - II: The Theory of Clonal Selection, 1971 November 24 (Box 3, Tape 103)
    - III: The Structure of Antibodies, 1971 November 29 (Box 3, Tape 104)
    - IV: Genetics and the Origin of Genetic Diversity, 1971 December 1 (Box 3, Tape 105)
    - V: Cell-Cell Interaction: Immune stimulation, Tolerance & Control, 1971 December 6 (Box 3, Tape 106)
    - VI: Some Prospects of Molecular Immunology, 1971 December 7 (Box 3, Tape 107)
  - Vincent Dole - Christmas Lecture: Drug Addiction, 1971 December 27 (Box 4, Tape 108-109)
  - Vincent Dole - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy, 1971 December 28 (Box 4, Tape 108-109)
  - Harvey Brooks - The Physical Sciences: Bellweather of Science Policy, 1972 January 13 (Box 4, Tape 110)
  - Henry W. Rieken - Social Change and Social Science, 1972 January 26 (Box 4, Tape 111)
  - Joseph S. Murtaugh - Biomedical Sciences, 1972 February 2 (Box 4, Tape 112)
  - Patrick E. Haggerty - Industrial Research and Development, 1972 March 16 (Box 4, Tape 113)
  - George E. Uhlenbeck - Darwin Lecture Series: Principles of Thermodynamics
    - I: The Concept of Temperature and Quantity of Heat. The First LAW, 1972 April 24 (Box 4, Tape 114)
    - II: The Second Law of Thermodynamics, 1972 April 27 (Box 4, Tape 115)
    - III: The Problems of Boltzmann, 1972 May 1 (Box 4, Tape 116)
    - IV: The Application of Thermodynamics, 1972 May 4 (Box 4, Tape 117)
  - Science and the Evolution of Public Policy (Box 4)
    - Edward E. David, Jr. - Federal Science and its Prospects, 1972 April 19 (Box 4, Tape 118)
    - Gerard Piel - The Role of Graduate Education, 1972 April 20 (Box 4, Tape 119)
    - Gerald Edelman - Nobel Prize Press Conference, 1972 October 20 (Box 4, Tape 120A-120B)
    - William Stein - Nobel Prize Press Conference, 1972 October 20 (Box 4, Tape 121)
    - Stanford Moore - Nobel Prize Press Conference, 1972 October 20 (Box 4)
    - Sidney Kingsley - RU Lecture: "Why I Didn't Write This Play", 1972 December 1 (Box 4, Tape 122)
    - Roger Payne - Christmas Lecture: whales, 1972 December 27-28 (Box 4, Tape 123A-123D)
  - Peter Karler - Darwin Lectures / Animal Behavior
    - I: Animal Behavior and Natural Selection, 1973 January 9 (Box 4, Tape 124)
    - II: The Stimulus Control of Behavior, 1973 January 12 (Box 4, Tape 125)
    - III: The Spontaneity of Behavior, 1973 January 16 (Box 4, Tape 126)
    - IV: Learning, Genetics and Behavioral Development, 1974 January 19 (Box 4, Tape 127)
  - Convocation, 1973 June 13 (Box 4, Tape 128A-128B)
  - Stanford Moore - RU Lecture: Experiments stemming from Basic Research on the Structure of Enzymes, 1973 March 2 (Box 4, Tape 129)
  - Maurice F. Strong - Fairfield Osborn Memorial Lecture: The Environment and the New Internationalism, 1973 October 18 (Box 4, Tape 130)
  - Wm. S. Paley. - Scientific Method In Science and Clinical Medicine, 1974 March 29 (Box 4, Tape 131)
  - James D. Watson - The First Two Years of the National Cancer Advisory Bd, 1974 April 5; 2 copies (Box 4, Tape 132)
  - TIAA-CREF Mtg. - Lecture to Employees with Question Period, 1975 April 29 (Box 4, Tape 134)
  - Lectures for Dr. Pfaffmann's Group
    - D. Pfaff - #8, 1969 April 4 (Box 4, Tape 135)
    - J. Weiss - #9, 1969 April 7 (Box 4, Tape 136)
    - I. Abramov - #11, 1969 April 18 (Box 4, Tape 137)
    - Bruce Knight, 1969 April 16 (Box 4, Tape 138)
    - Ratliff - #12, 1969 April 21 (Box 4, Tape 139)
  - G.A. Miller, 1969 April 28 1969 April 30 (Box 4, Tape 140)
    Scope and Contents note
    Side 1
  - Tom Bever, 1969 May 2 (Box 4, Tape 140)
    Side 2
  - E. Ligon, 1969 May 5 (Box 4, Tape 141)
  - W.K. Estes, 1969 May 7 (Box 4, Tape 142)
  - W.K. Estes, 1969 May 9 (Box 4, Tape 143)
  - Ludwig Edelstein - Plato's Seventh letter: an example of historic verification, 1964 October 30 (Box 5)